what's the biggest number no really I'm
serious and I don't mean Infinity I mean
like an actual largest number you could
write down I promise there's a real
answer so come with me down this crazy
rabbit hole because we're going all the
way to the
[Music]
bottom but first today's sponsor
brilliant brilliant is where you learn
by doing with thousands of interactive
lessons and math data analytics
programming and a I brilliant is
uniquely effective to help teach you
difficult subjects from the ground up
build your critical thinking skills
through problem solving not memorizing I
really enjoyed their programming with
python course with so many interactive
examples brilliant makes it really fun
to learn with bite-sized lessons you can
do every day whenever you have time to
try everything brilliant has to offer
for free for a full 30 days visit
brilliant.org Cod parade or click on the
link in the description you'll also Al
get 20% off an annual premium
subscription thanks brilliant so back to
the question we need to set some kind of
limit on how much space we're allowed to
use to write down this number but the
exact size we choose won't really matter
because whatever Technique we come up
with should generalize if we want to use
a different size so just for fun let's
limit ourselves to the largest number
that could fit in a single SMS text
message that's 160 characters or 140
bytes yeah I know it's weird for some
reason SMS is only seven bits per
character naively we could just fill up
the whole thing with nines and that
gives us a number about 10 to the 160 so
we'll add that to the leaderboard but
obviously we can do better than that I
mean I was able to write it on the
leaderboard in way less space if we
include basic math symbols we could
instead make a Power Tower like this
which is already unfathomably large but
this might as well be zero compared to
where we're going I mean while we're
using math symbols technically we could
have a nine followed by 159
factorials that's definitely larger but
come on that's still smaller than
well-known numbers like grams number in
fact couldn't we just write Gram's
number or Gram's number to the power of
Gram's number or G number followed by as
many factorials as we could fit I guess
but if we can use Gram's number what's
stopping us from using any other large
number you can think of the problem is
we can't Define our number off screen
and then just write its name that's
cheating because really that's using
more symbols and bytes than the rules
allow it also wouldn't be fair to only
write a definition of the number if
there's no way to actually know its
value it's uncomputable
we should include all the necessary
instructions to actually generate the
number for it to count fine then here's
a Python program that would
theoretically generate grams number if
you had unlimited computing power and It
just fits into the 140 bytes okay fine
that seems fair to add to the
leaderboard but is python really the
best way to make a large number surely
there's programming languages that are
more compact allowing more space to make
even larger numbers for example here's a
significantly smaller grams number
program written in hasell but now there
is another dilemma if we can just pick
any programming language there could
just be some obscure language that
happens to have the exact function or
number we need as part of the syntax I
mean at some point is it really any
different than just writing down the
name of the number what should even
count as a valid programming language
where do we draw the line should python
even count what about math symbols in
general that's kind of like a
language okay if we want to Define
numbers with programs we need something
as basic and Universal as possible
something so simple even aliens could
decipher it and there's a few candidates
for that the first is a turing machine
which is an infinite tape with the a set
of States rules and starting conditions
the head reads the tape and then changes
state flips bits and moves the tape it's
certainly better but it still feels a
bit clunky and artificial and It's
tricky to see how you'd encode a turing
machine into a message in a universal
way luckily there is an even better
option and that's Lambda
Calculus if you've never heard of it
before it's basically a programming
language
that only has one function the Lambda
plus parentheses and variables that's it
literally nothing else no numbers no
data structures no math strings Loops
conditionals anything that's what makes
it so Universal you define all those
things yourself nothing is taken for
granted so how do you even Define a
number in a language that has no numbers
the most common way in Lambda calc
is with something called Church numerals
in that system the number of times you
apply a function represents the number
so not applying F at all is zero
applying f one time is one applying it
twice is two and so on to make loops and
conditionals you can use certain Lambda
Expressions called combinators in fact
there's a whole alphabet of combinators
from a to Omega for all sorts of things
you'd expect effect in a programming
language it can often be hard to follow
what these Lambda Expressions do but one
cool way to help visualize them is with
these Lambda diagrams invented by John
Trump it's a really nice way to directly
turn linear code into 2D images and
there's just something very satisfying
about it so here's yet again another
program to make grams number but this
time as a Lambda expression it does take
up quite a bit of space though but we
don't actually need this many symbols
anymore in fact there is a natural
extension to something called binary
Lambda calculus or BLC which uses
different bit patterns to represent the
symbols in a much more compact way using
BLC we can actually compress this down
to only 15 bytes and it can get really
compressed here's another program that
outputs a number even larger than GS
number number that's only 49 bits long
yes bits not bites that would fit in
only seven characters of a text message
that's great we have a super Compact and
Universal system to make really big
numbers so what's the answer what's the
biggest number well unfortunately it's
impossible to know the exact number I
mean it is out there somewhere but even
if we had unlimited comput computational
power to check every possible bit
pattern there's still no way to
algorithmically check if a Lambda
expression terminates or expands forever
in a loop it's the classic halting
problem but that doesn't mean we can't
get
close let's go back to some classic
operators each one can be defined as
repeating the previous operation that
many times for example if we have a
function which Returns the next number
apply applying that repeatedly is just
addition and applying addition
repeatedly is just multiplication and
next is exponents and that can be
extended as far as we want but since
we're using a number here that number
could itself be an expression to
determine which operation we want to do
so let's define this new expression
where we plug in the same variable into
the operator this expression is often
written as f
Omega yes that Omega is an infinite
ordinal but to be clear there's nothing
infinite about this function it just
grows faster than any finite number you
could put here as X gets larger so it's
just a useful
notation okay but let's keep continuing
the pattern what would happen if we
apply X applications of f
Omega well obviously that's F Omega + 1
and of course that could go on forever
and hey what do you know we have another
number here that could plug into itself
and continuing the notation we now have
omega plus Omega or 2 Omega and we could
keep doing this to get 3 Omega 4 Omega
hey look another number plug it into
itself for Omega Omega or Omega
squared and as you can imagine this
process can continue for a long time you
can get omegas to the power of omegas go
past the transfinite omegas into the
epsilons you can run out of Greek
letters and parameterize that let's just
say it gets insane and it's really
really hard to describe just how fast
these functions grow and how large these
numbers can get so I think now we have
all the tools we need to finally answer
the question what is the fastest growing
largest ordinal function we could fit
into a text message
well the fastest one I could find that
definitely fits is the buck holes
ordinal it's really hard to describe
just how fast it grows but it does have
a nice tree based construction similar
to the famous tree function but it's
much much faster growing than that
surprisingly the Buckle's ordinal
function only takes 49 bytes at most so
there's still a ton of room to do way
more to it but what you have to
understand is that when you get to this
level of growth it doesn't really matter
what number you put here or how you
construct it it's not going to change
its position on the leaderboard even if
we apply it to itself that many times
we're only adding one to the ordinal the
next fastest growing ordinal will just
completely dominate it no matter what we
do so just for fun let's plug in these
numbers and call it a day this number
number dominates almost any other
well-known computable number so I think
I'm satisfied enough to end it here a
huge shout out to John Trump for all his
help in researching this video he
pioneered a lot of the techniques I've
used in this video so big thanks for
that and before I go don't forget to
check out my game 4D golf on Steam it's
actually on sale for a limited time
right now there's still been a steady
stream of updates with new courses on
the Steam Workshop new languages and a
ton of overall improvements and it
really supports the channel and thanks
for watching